Guide to the Rochambeau Papers and Rochambeau Family Cartographic Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence to Rochambeau, 1780-94; Series I; 1.7; (4 boxes)
  - FRENCH DIPLOMATS IN AMERICA
    - La Luzerne, Anne-César, chevalier de
      - Note, in French, in a secretary's hand concerning Rochambeau's correspondence with La Luzerne. 1 page, 4to. No place., [1780] (Box 2, Folder 135)
        Rochambeau's secretary notes that a letter was sent to La Luzerne on July 12, 1780, just after the former's arrival at Newport, of which no copy was kept.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Jan 6 (Box 2, Folder 136)
        Concerns financial difficulties in Philadelphia. In response to an appeal from Rochambeau, he says that he is able to furnish only 40 to 60,000 livres, and that money is extremely scarce.
      - Letter signed. 10 1/2 pages, folio. Partly in code, with accompanying decode on a separate page. Philadelphia., 1781 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 137)
        A long description of the revolt of the Pennsylvania troops. He goes on to describe, in the coded portion of the letter, the panic which affected some members of Congress.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Jan 10 (Box 2, Folder 138)
        Further news of the revolt of the Pennsylvania troops, with a description of their rejection of the offers of an emissary from Clinton.
      - Letter signed. 3 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 139)
        Military news from the South; the reinforcement of Cornwallis by General Leslie; the position of Greene's troops; the movements of Benedict Arnold in Virginia. He assures Rochambeau that his answer to Washington regarding a combined operation with some Spanish troops in the South was the right one.
      - Letter signed. 6 pages, folio. Mostly in code, with accompanying separate decode, 2 1/4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 140)
        Deals at length with the financially embarrassed position of the French forces, and also urges that a raid be made by the fleet in Chesapeake Bay.
      - Autograph letter signed. 3 pages, 8vo. Philadelphia., [1781] Feb 12 (Box 3, Folder 141)
        News of the siege of Gibraltar, of the arrival of Rochambeau's son in France, and of the business negotiations relative to the sale of drafts on France.
      - Letter signed. 3 pages, folio. Partly in code, with accompanying decode, 1 page, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Feb 25 (Box 3, Folder 142)
        Writes about the raid carried out in Chesapeake Bay by a battleship and two frigates under the command of Tilly; about the impending campaign of the Spaniards under the command of Galvez against Pensacola; and about Washington's correspondence with Rochambeau regarding a stronger attack against the British in Chesapeake Bay.
      - Letter signed. 2 1/2 pages, folio. Mostly in code, with decode on an accompanying sheet, 1 1/4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Feb 25 (Box 3, Folder 143)
        Discusses a loan made by Mr. Price which needed to be repaid, and suggests that a fast-sailing frigate be sent to Havana, where funds would be available.
      - Letter signed. 3 1/2 pages, folio. Almost entirely in code, with accompanying decode, 1 1/4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Mar 3 (Box 3, Folder 144)
        Agrees with Rochambeau's plan to send an expedition to Chesapeake Bay, and informs him that Lafayette is already at the head of the Bay, waiting for him there. He also gives news of the march of Lord Cornwallis' army to Virginia.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. With translation into French of a letter of Thomas Jefferson, "Copie d'une Lettre de Mr. Jefferson au President du Congres en datte de Richmond le 26. Fevr.," 1 1/2 pages, 4to. [Philadelphia.], 1781 Mar 5 (Box 3, Folder 145)
        Jefferson's letter gives an overview of the state of Cornwallis' army, which leads La Luzerne to predict a "seconde affaire de Saratoga." On the date the word "mai" has been crossed through.
      - Letter signed. 4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Mar 6 (Box 3, Folder 146)
        A long description of the course of the war in the South. Morgan's victory over Tarleton at Cowpens is described, as well as the complicated maneuvers between Greene and Cornwallis, the attacks by the Creek and Cherokee Indians on the frontiers, and the Arnold expedition in Chesapeake Bay.
      - Autograph letter signed. 3 pages, 8vo. [Philadelphia], [1781 Mar 10] (Box 3, Folder 147)
        Results of the raid to Chesapeake Bay by Tilly. He repeats his plea for Rochambeau to send a ship to Havana to obtain hard cash.
      - Letter signed. 4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Mar 14 (Box 3, Folder 148)
        Another plea for settlement of the French debts at Philadelphia. He reveals that the failure of reinforcements for the Rhode Island fleet to arrive was caused by the fact that Admiral de Guichen did not give the code book to Admiral de Monteil, who was therefore unable to read his letters. Lafayette has sailed down Chesapeake Bay, and is waiting at Annapolis to go farther.
      - Letter signed. 2 1/4 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode. Philadelphia., 1781 Mar 20 (Box 3, Folder 149)
        More about the missing ships. He urges Rochambeau to send news of the true state of affairs to France immediately, so that there will be no mistaken assumptions when plans were made. He repeats the story of his previous letter about the missing code book.
      - Letter signed. 7 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode, and an accompanying paper, "Subsistance de L'armee" dated Philadelphie le 26. mars 1781, 2 1/2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Mar 27 (Box 3, Folder 150)
        The enclosure is a copy of his communication to a committee of Congress which dealt with the Franklin- Necker contract. In the letter, in a coded portion, he states that he has written to the French government about the precarious financial situation. He also recommends that subsidy funds sent from France be kept strictly secret, as they would otherwise be wasted or cause a slackening of efforts by Congress.
      - Letter signed. 3 1/2 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode. Philadelphia., 1781 Apr 3 (Box 3, Folder 151)
        Expresses his regret that the Chesapeake expedition under Destouches has been so unfruitful, and calls for action in the South. He thanks Rochambeau for the settlement of the Price loan in specie, and condemns the conduct of Holker.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., [1781] Apr 7 (Box 3, Folder 152)
        Tells Rochambeau that the battle of Cape Henry has greatly changed the opinion of Americans about the French navy. He informs Rochambeau that a great naval force was being prepared in France, probably for America, and that it was of the greatest importance that both Rochambeau and the American army be ready to act when assistance comes.
      - Letter signed. 4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Apr 8 (Box 3, Folder 153)
        More about the financing of the French army. He again objects to the financial dealings of Holker.
      - Letter signed. 4 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode. With an enclosure, "Lettre du Général Washington à Mr. Lund Washington en Virginie interceptée par les anglois et publiée dans le papier de New-York," 2 1/2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Apr 13 (Box 3, Folder 154)
        Sends Rochambeau a translation into French of the intercepted letter from George Washington to Lund Washington, and tells him that he saw no harm in the criticism. He also writes about relieving the Southern States, about the intention of the French ministry to send further help to America, and again about the necessity of keeping secret any funds sent to America as a subsidy. He also mentions the Franklin-Necker contract.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, 4to. With an enclosure, "By the united States in Congress assembled. April 11th. 1781. Resolved... Charles Thomson Secreta.," 1 page, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Apr 16 (Box 3, Folder 155)
        He forwards to Rochambeau a copy of a Resolution of Congress stating that they will "take every measure in their power for furnishing the supplies to the amount of four hundred thousand Dollars...."
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode. With an enclosure, in French, 2 pages 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Apr 24 (Box 3, Folder 156)
        Sends extracts from letters of Vergennes and Castries regarding the failure of Admiral de Monteil to send five additional ships to Rhode Island.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 1/4 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 157)
        The latest news from the South.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. With an enclosure, "Lettre de Mr. Le Ch. De La Luzerne a Mr. Destouches du 7. may 1781," 3 1/4 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode. Philadelphia., 1781 May 7 (Box 3, Folder 158)
        A plea for an expedition to Chesapeake Bay. The enclosure is a decipher of a letter to Destouches about the situation in the Southern States, and suggesting that if the French ships could change their base to the Bay, that the pressure against these States would be relieved.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 May 8 (Box 3, Folder 159)
        Concerns the crash of the Continental currency. A sentence which has been heavily marked over relates to the Washington letter criticizing the French Admirals.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 160)
        News of the fleet from France, and of the state of affairs in Virginia.
      - Letter signed. 2 1/2 pages, folio. With an enclosure, in French, "Memoire," signed. 7 1/2 pages, folio. Blank corner torn from last page. philadelphie le 20 avril [i.e. may?] 1781. Philadelphia., 1781 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 161)
        Urges speed in starting the coming campaign. Enclosure contains his ideas for the coming campaign. It is certain that the April date is a clerical error, as on the next to last page he refers to the impending conference between Rochambeau and Washington, which took place on May 23rd. He urges that all naval and land forces available be sent to Chesapeake Bay.
      - Letter signed. 3 pages, folio. Partly in code, with interlinear decode. With an enclosed copy of a letter to Washington, Philae. le 1er. Juin 1781. 2 1/2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Jun 1 (Box 3, Folder 162)
        He repeats his fears that the southern states will be forced to make peace with the British. In the enclosed letter, a reply to Washington's letter of May 23rd, he also informs Washington that the French government is granting a subsidy of 6,000,000 livres.
      - Letter signed. 1 1/2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Jun 11 (Box 3, Folder 163)
        Expresses his dissatisfaction with the results of the Wethersfield Conference.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. Philadelphia., [1781] Jun 22 (Box 3, Folder 164)
        News of the arrival of a British convoy and of a small reinforcement for the garrisons of Charleston, St. Augustine, etc.
      - Letter signed. 3 1/2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Aug 3 (Box 3, Folder 165)
        Regards Robert Morris' proposal for the furnishing of supplies to the French army. He praises Morris' measures for the establishment of American credit.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Aug 5 (Box 3, Folder 166)
        Reports has heard no news whatever concerning the fleet of Admiral de Grasse.
      - Letter signed. One sentence in code, with interlinear decode. 1 page, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Aug 13 (Box 3, Folder 167)
        News of Cornwallis' retreat to Yorktown.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, 4to. Mostly in code, with interlinear decode. Philadelphia., 1781 Aug 17 (Box 3, Folder 168)
        News that de Grasse is expected momentarily at Cap Français, St. Domingue.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 1/2 pages, 4to. With 3 enclosures, all in French: "Copie d'une Lettre de Mr. le Comte de Grasse à M. le Chevalier de la Luzerne, du Cap le 28. Juillet 1781." 2 pages, folio, mostly in code with interlinear decode; "Copie d'une Lettre trouvée à Bord d'un paque bot D'Antigue qui a été pris et conduit dans le Port de Philadelphie...Signé Richd. Nash. - Antigue le 6. Aout 1781." 1 1/2 pages 4to.; "A Philadelphie le 21 aout 1781." 1 1/2 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Aug 21 (Box 3, Folder 169)
        The latest news from de Grasse. He encloses a copy of the Admiral's letter to him which is substantially the same as de Grasse's letter to Rochambeau. The other two enclosures relate to news of the return of Admiral Hood's fleet to England.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. [Philadelphia], [1781 Aug] (Box 3, Folder 170)
        Miscellaneous news of naval affairs in Europe.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages (including postscript), folio. With an enclosure, "Nouvelles de Newyorck. 7bre. 1781," 1 page, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Sep 14 (Box 3, Folder 171)
        Information on changes in the British naval command. In a postscript, and on the enclosed paper, he tells of reported ship movements in New York, which were apparently sending troops to Virginia.
      - Letter signed. 4 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Oct 1 (Box 3, Folder 172)
        News of the naval battle off Chesapeake Bay between the fleets of de Grasse and Graves. He also writes about the supply of flour for the army, the possibility of an attack on Philadelphia, and money for the army.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Oct 5 (Box 3, Folder 173)
        Concerns the arrival of funds for the French army.
      - Letter signed. 1 1/2 pages, 4to. With an autograph notation by Rochambeau. Philadelphia., 1781 Nov 17 (Box 3, Folder 174)
        Suggests that a chain of dispatch riders be established between the French and American headquarters. Rochambeau's note states that the letter was received Dec. 15.
      - Autograph letter signed. 3 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Nov 27 (Box 3, Folder 175)
        Warns that money he is expecting from France may not arrive as soon as he expects; also mentions ship movements, the exchange of prisoners, etc.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 1/2 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Nov 13 (Box 3, Folder 176)
        News that Lafayette, leaving for France, will carry Rochambeau's dispatches to the French government. He complains of the slow mail service, and says that any news reaching Philadelphia will be sent on immediately.
      - Letter signed. 2 1/4 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Nov 24 (Box 3, Folder 177)
        Because of the failure of funds to arrive from France, he recommends raising money in Philadelphia by drafts on France, which he says are nearly at par.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Dec 24 (Box 3, Folder 178)
        News of the capture of a French vessel bound for Havana.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, 4to. Philadelphia., 1781 Dec 26 (Box 3, Folder 179)
        Requests that if money is needed later, it not be raised by paying the contractors for supplies in paper, but by dealing with financiers in Philadelphia, as there is less loss that way.
    - Menonville, François-Louis-Thibaut de.
      Unless otherwise indicated, all letters from Menonville to Rochambeau are in French.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 180)
        A report on his mission to obtain supplies, and his difficulties because of the total collapse of the Continental paper currency.
      - Autograph letter signed. 3 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 May 16 (Box 3, Folder 181)
        A further report on the difficulties caused in financing the French army in America, because of the fall of Continental paper money. He suggests some cost-saving measures.
      - Autograph letter signed, from Vioménil, Antoine Charles du Houx, Baron de to Menonville, in French. 4 pages, 4to. Newport., 1781 May 24 (Box 3, Folder 182)
        A reply on behalf of Rochambeau, to Menonville's two letters. He expresses complete approval of the course Menonville has taken in not contracting for supplies in Philadelphia, and tells him that Rochambeau is contracting in New England for what the army needed.
      - Autograph letter signed. 3 1/2 pages, folio. Philadelphia., 1781 Jun 4 (Box 3, Folder 183)
        Concerning the financial and supply situation, with some military news. After a long discussion of the purchases of supplies made by the French agents, he reports on a discussion with Robert Morris. He also gives the latest news of operations by Generals Greene, Cornwallis, and Lafayette.
  - FRENCH NAVY IN AMERICA
    - Washington to Admiral Ternay
      - Copy of a letter ("au quartier général de Bergen County Le 16. 7bre. 1780") and annexed intelligence report ("du 14. 7bre.") to Admiral Ternay, translated into French. 1 1/2 pages, 4to., [1780 Sep 16] (Box 3, Folder 184)
    - Grandchain de Semonville, Guillaume J. C. L. de
      - Autograph letter signed, to La Pérouse, in French. 3 pages, 4to. Newport., 1781 Mar 4 (Box 3, Folder 185)
        The latest news from the French headquarters in Newport regarding orders from Destouches, then in command of the Newport fleet. He also writes of an exchange of prisoners, and of financial matters.
    - Grasse, François Joseph Paul de Grasse, comte de
      Unless otherwise indicated, all letters from de Grasse to Rochambeau are in French.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. "A Bord de la ville de paris en mer." With an autograph note by Rochambeau on the first page. With enclosed list of de Grasse's fleet. 2 pages, folio., 1781 Mar 29 (Box 3, Folder 186)
        A report that the French fleet is under way, and that it will be ready to participate in an offensive against the English armies during the summer. With an accompanying list of the naval forces under his command. Rochambeau's note on the first page states that he received it on the 10th of June when his army was just setting out from Providence.
      - Letter signed. 2 pages, folio. With an autograph postscript by de Grasse. Cap-François, St. Domingue., 1781 Jul 28 (Box 3, Folder 187)
        Concerns the beginning of the Yorktown campaign. He states he will leave with 25 to 29 warships on August 3 to Chesapeake Bay, and that he can remain no longer than the 15th of October. The postscript, in the handwriting of de Grasse, relates to the furnishing of pilots for Chesapeake Bay. This letter is listed and reproduced in The American Campaigns of Rochambeau's Army 1780, 1781, 1782, 1783, trans. and ed. by Howard C. Rice, Jr., and Anne S. K. Brown, Vol. I, pp. xvii-xviii and between pp. 60 and 61. It was exhibited at the National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution, in the 1981 exhibition, "By Sea and Land: Independence with the Help of France."
      - Retained copy of a letter, from Washington and Rochambeau to de Grasse. 6 1/2 pages, folio. "Camp at Phillipsburg." With an autograph translation into French by Rochambeau, 1 1/2 pages, folio., 1781 Aug 17 (Box 3, Folder 188)
        The decision to engage the British in Virginia rather than attack New York. They go on to present three possible scenarios after the French fleet's arrival in the Chesapeake and suggested action regarding each. This is Rochambeau's file copy.
      - Letter signed. 2 1/2 pages, 4to. "dans la baye de Chesapeack, A Bord De La Ville de Paris.", 1781 Aug 30 (Box 3, Folder 189)
        Announcement of his arrival. He also discusses the events of his voyage, and other military details, ending with his pledge to do all he can to establish American independence.
      - Letter to La Luzerne (copy). 3/4 page, 4to. Directly below is a letter to La Luzerne from Lafayette (copy). 2 1/4 pages, 4to. "Dattée de la Baye de Chesapeack le 30 aout 1781." [and] "de holts forge le 1 7bre." [1781], respectively., [1781 Sep 1] (Box 3, Folder 190)
        De Grasse announces his arrival in American waters. Lafayette gives a detailed account of the positions of his forces and the enemy, and of the plans he has for containing Cornwallis until the French-American army arrives.
      - Letter signed. 1 page, folio. "au Cap henry.", 1781 Sep 2 (Box 3, Folder 191)
        Written in reply to a joint letter from Rochambeau and Washington. He writes that he has only warships with him, and gives details of the operations against Cornwallis conducted by Lafayette and Saint-Simon.
      - Letter signed. 1 page, 4to. "au Cap henry.", 1781 Sep 4 (Box 3, Folder 192)
        A report on the readiness of ships to transport troops.
      - Letter signed. 3 pages, folio. With autograph postscript by de Grasse. "a bord de la ville de Paris.", 1781 Sep 24 (Box 3, Folder 193)
        States he will keep his fleet at the same mooring in order to prevent a British force from entering Chesapeake Bay. He requests water, firewood, and fresh supplies for his sick.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 1/2 pages, 4to. "Ville De paris a 1 heur apres mid.", 1781 Sep 24 (Box 3, Folder 194)
        A sudden change of plans, that, as soon as the winds will permit, he will sail from the Bay, and gives instructions as to how to return the infantry and artillery troops to the West Indies.
      - Letter signed. 3 pages, 4to. [Chesapeake Bay; there is a pencil notation on the first page of the letter, "c. Aug. 30 - Sept. 4, 1781."] 1781 [Sep 25] (Box 3, Folder 195)
        Concerns the arrangements for the accommodation of the French fleet. The first two lines of the letter are in the handwriting of Lafayette.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 1/4 pages, 4to. [Chesapeake Bay.] Addressed on p. 4, 1781 Sep 29 (Box 3, Folder 196)
        Agrees to supply 800 more men from the fleet to take part in the operations against Yorktown. He notes that he has a large number of sick and wounded and will be shorthanded after sending the 800 men.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. [Chesapeake Bay; there is a pencil notation at the bottom of the first page of the letter, "(ca. Oct. 1, 1781).] Addressed on p. 4., 1781 [Oct 1] (Box 3, Folder 197)
        A demand that the French navy be kept informed of the progress of the siege of Yorktown, by receiving a daily bulletin.
      - Letter signed. 1 1/2 pages, folio. [Chesapeake Bay], le 5 8bre. 1781. With an enclosed report, "Rapport fait par le commandant d'un Bateau arrêté en sortant de la Riviere D'york, par les chalouppe des Vaisseaux qui en ferment le Blocus." 2 pages, 4to., 1781 Oct 4 (Box 3, Folder 198)
        Concerns the progress of the Yorktown siege. He warns that his ships can accomplish nothing because of the lack of pilots; speaks of his lack of bread on the ships, and other matters. The report of the ship's officer, who had been captured attempting to escape from Yorktown in a small vessel, gives a picture of events within the besieged town.
      - Autograph letter signed. 1 page, 4to. [Chesapeake Bay], "a 8 heur sur Matin." Addressed on p. 4., 1781 Oct 7 (Box 3, Folder 199)
        Concerns the bombardment of Yorktown by the French and American forces, which he had heard from the Bay.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 pages, 4to. [Chesapeake Bay]., 1781 Oct 10 (Box 3, Folder 200)
        Complains of the lack of flour in the fleet, and the methods for getting a supply to him.
      - Autograph letter signed. 2 1/2 pages, 4to. [Chesapeake Bay]., 1781 Oct 11 (Box 3, Folder 201)